<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catholick loyalty upon the subject of government and obedience : delivered in a sermon before the King and Queen in His Majesties Chappel-Royal at White-Hall on the thirtieth of January, 1687 / by the Reverend Father Edward Scarisbrike ...</title>
            <author>Scarisbrike, Edward, 1639-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13593405</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13593405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62305)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 802:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catholick loyalty upon the subject of government and obedience : delivered in a sermon before the King and Queen in His Majesties Chappel-Royal at White-Hall on the thirtieth of January, 1687 / by the Reverend Father Edward Scarisbrike ...</title>
                  <author>Scarisbrike, Edward, 1639-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Booker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs VIII, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Government, Resistance to --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Government, Resistance to --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100684:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100684:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Catholick Loyalty:</hi> UPON THE SUBJECT OF GOVERNMENT and OBEDIENCE.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN A SERMON, BEFORE THE King and Queen In his Majeſties Chappel-Royal at <hi>WHITE-HALL,</hi> On the <hi>Thirtieth of January,</hi> 1687.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. VIII. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Per me Reges Regnant: By Me Kings Reign.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by his Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Reverend Father <hi>EDWARD SCARISBRIKE,</hi> Prieſt of the Society of JESUS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Booker.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100684:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100684:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS Sacred Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Duty and Obedience to Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Order, and in a moſt Profound and Reverential Acknowledgment of the Honour of Your Royal Command, I have preſumed to lay theſe Papers at Your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Feet, as the truly <hi>Catholick Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of that Society, whereof the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hath the Honour to be a Member; and who is, to the higheſt degree of Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>The moſt Dutiful of your Majeſties Subjects; <hi>EDWARD SCARISBRIKE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:100684:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100684:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Catholick Loyalty:</hi> Upon the Subject of GOVERNMENT and OBEDIENCE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. VIII. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Per me Reges Regnant. By me Kings Reign.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HEre is a whole Sermon (Sacred Majeſty) wrapt up in a ſhort Text, of only <hi>four words, Per me Reges Regnant:</hi> And in this plain, ſhort Text, the Wiſdom of God Preaches to the Sons of men. It Preaches, I ſay, to All, without Exception; to Rulers as well as to Subjects. It admoniſheth Kings, by whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion they <hi>Govern,</hi> and Inſtructs the People at the ſame time, whom they are to <hi>Obey.</hi> If the <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable Doctrine,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconteſtable Authority</hi> of this <hi>Emphatical</hi> Portion of Holy Writ, had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Thought and laid to Heart, when time was, as it ought to have been; there wou'd have been no occaſion for the Ruful Solemnity of this days meeting: No Subject for an <hi>Anniverſary,</hi> in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Memory (and Deteſtation) of ſo Execrable,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100684:4"/>Treaſonous and Barbarous a <hi>Regicide:</hi> A <hi>Regicide,</hi> committed in the Face of the Sun in <hi>Cold Blood,</hi> and under a Pretext of Law; Nay, and to conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the wickedneſs, by the Hands of <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Subjects,</hi> and before the very Gate of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns Royal Palace.</p>
            <p>This is not a place or an Argument for high Flights, or florid Diſcourſes; but without more words, it was a <hi>Diabolical</hi> Violence upon the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of a <hi>Lawful,</hi> a <hi>Juſt,</hi> a <hi>Merciful</hi> and moſt <hi>Excellent Prince.</hi> Now if <hi>Innocent Blood</hi> ſhall <hi>deſite</hi> a Land, even in a <hi>private, ſingle</hi> caſe of <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> and barely for defacing the Image of God in a kind of <hi>Theological Alluſion</hi> or <hi>Figure;</hi> what Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may not a Nation reaſonably dread, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, from Gods <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Vengeance,</hi> for ſo <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal,</hi> ſo <hi>Daring,</hi> ſo <hi>Complicated a Murder</hi> as this was! A <hi>Murder,</hi> that carried <hi>Oppreſſion, Treaſon, Sacriledge,</hi> and the whole Roll of <hi>Crying Mortal Sins</hi> in the Veins of it. A <hi>Murder,</hi> that ſtruck at the <hi>Divinity</hi> of Power, as well as at the <hi>Administration</hi> of it; and at the ſame time attacqued the Life of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and bid a defiance to his Royal <hi>Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this conſideration it is, that we are called together to Humble our ſelves before Almighty God, with Faſting and Prayers, to Implore the <hi>Divine Mercy</hi> to accept of our true Repentance and hearty Contrition for all our by-paſt heinous Sins, and grant us his holy Grace, that we may live here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in perfect Union and Charity, and in a duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100684:4"/>Obedience to God and our Governours, and in Love, Peace and Agreement with one another. For this reaſon it is, that we are now met to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate our ſelves before the Father of Mercies, moſt fervently to beſeech him in his Infinite Goodneſs, to be Gratious to our Brethren, as well as to our ſelves; and to avert that deſtroying Vengeance which we may ſo juſtly fear, and cannot but trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under the thought of, for the almoſt inexpiable Sin of Blaſpheming Gods Anointed, and for the effuſion of his Blood. Not but that I do in Charity hope, and in a full perſwaſion of Reaſon preſume, that every Soul that hears me this day, can lay his Hand upon his Heart, and acquit himſelf of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had any part in this Helliſh Tragedy, either in Thought, Word or Deed, in a direct tendency to ſo black an end. We cannot ſo much forget the Duties of our Profeſſion, either as Chriſtians, as Catholicks, or as Subjects, for we have been taught better things; But a National Wickedneſs we know, calls for a National Puniſhment. And briefly, Be it what it will, we are all Offenders, all Provokers, and every good Chriſtian is to bear his own Burthen without Criminating <hi>Inſtruments</hi> or <hi>Parties.</hi> No, Beloved Chriſtians, <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> is the Work and Duty of the day: and it wou'd have a very ill Grace, whilſt we are upon our bended Knees, in Supplications to the Diſpencer of all Mercies, for an Act of <hi>Oblivion for our ſelves;</hi> at the ſame time not to allow an <hi>Amne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty one to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100684:5"/>
            <p>But to haſten to my buſineſs, Here is a horrid thing done, which moſt certainly wou'd never have been done, if the Doers of it had but kept ſeriouſly in their thoughts theſe words, <hi>Per me Reges Regnant, By me Kings Reign;</hi> and I do not know a better preſervative for the future, againſt theſe Principles and Practices, that wrought all Our former Miſery and Woe, than a plain Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this Text, <hi>Per me Reges Regnant.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Non est poteſtas niſi a Deo,</hi> C. xiii. V. 1. <hi>ad Rom.</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it ſelf,</hi> and all the <hi>Powers of Government,</hi> are of Divine Appointment and Inſtitution: And this ſhall be the firſt point of my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now if it be granted, that <hi>Government</hi> is of God, it follows neceſſarily, that <hi>Subjection</hi> muſt be ſo too; for <hi>Order</hi> is the <hi>Excellency of Power it ſelf;</hi> and they derive both from the ſame Fountain. <hi>Superior</hi> is <hi>Nonſenſe</hi> without <hi>Inferior:</hi> and the <hi>Relatives</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand one without another. If <hi>Governors</hi> be from <hi>God,</hi> ſo are the <hi>Governed;</hi> if <hi>Power,</hi> ſo is <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</hi> Briefly, I find one Propoſition here invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in another; and that the <hi>Obedience</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> falls as naturally within the proſpect of my Text, as the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Prince:</hi> and ſince they cannot be ſeparated, I ſhall treat of both. Firſt, of <hi>Government,</hi> how ſacred it is, as being of <hi>Divine Authority.</hi> Secondly, of <hi>Obedience;</hi> with <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Applications</hi> ſuitable to the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Occaſion.</hi> They are both joyned in the <hi>Methods</hi> of Gods <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> in <hi>Nature, Reaſon, Religion, Policy, Law,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100684:5"/>Practice:</hi> In a word, the ſame Power which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points Kings to <hi>Command,</hi> obligeth <hi>Subjects</hi> to <hi>Obey.</hi> To underſtand theſe two important Truths, we muſt beg the Aſſiſtance of the King of Kings and and Lord of all Powers, by the Interceſſion of the Virgin <hi>Mary. Ave Maria.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The First Part.</head>
               <p>IT is obſervable, that in the whole Book of Life, we do not find any thing more plainly ſet down, more accurately read upon, or oftner inculcated, than the Doctrine of the <hi>ſacredneſs</hi> of <hi>Governing Powers,</hi> which is no more at laſt than what natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reſults from the very words of my Text: <hi>By me Kings Reign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To begin with the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> give me leave to put three ſhort <hi>Queries:</hi> 1. This <hi>Power; Is it ſo ſacred?</hi> 2. <hi>Are we very certain that it is ſo?</hi> 3. With reverence to the Suppoſition, <hi>What if it be?</hi> I anſwer in order: Firſt, That it is as ſacred as the having God the <hi>Author</hi> of it, can make any thing. Secondly, We have the <hi>Veracity</hi> of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> that ſo it is; and laſtly, <hi>If ſo it be;</hi> there is no contending with an <hi>Almighty Power,</hi> who hath placed Governours and Rulers over us; no expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating with an <hi>Infallible Wiſdom,</hi> who knows what is beſt for us; no playing faſt and looſe with an <hi>All-ſeeing God,</hi> who inſpects the Thoughts as well as the Actions: There is no room in this caſe either
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100684:6"/>for <hi>Fallacy,</hi> or <hi>force; Arms,</hi> or <hi>Arguments:</hi> But the Decretory four words here in my Text, <hi>By me Kings Reign,</hi> confounds all <hi>Sophiſms,</hi> diſſolves all <hi>Scruples,</hi> ſtops all mouths, and ſilences all Diſputes. The challenges of the People, as if Authority were radically in them; the contradictory perſwaſions of <hi>Co-ordinacy;</hi> that is to ſay, of a ſharing of <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> amongſt <hi>Subjects;</hi> the fancy of a <hi>Conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power,</hi> and a <hi>Conditional Duty;</hi> (as if <hi>Kings</hi> were only the <hi>Truſtees</hi> of the <hi>People</hi>) the Paradox of a <hi>ſingulis major, univerſis minor;</hi> the conceit of erecting <hi>Government</hi> upon the ſandy foundation of a diffuſive <hi>multitude:</hi> Take all theſe Cavils and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and as many more of the ſame kind as were ever hammer'd out by the malice and wit of Hell, and corrupt Nature: In theſe two little ſyllables, <hi>Per me, By me;</hi> they are all anſwered and put to flight like the duſt before the wind, and beyond all thought or poſſibility of reſource: Unleſs they will appeal from the <hi>Potter</hi> to the <hi>Clay;</hi> from <hi>Omnipotence</hi> to <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blond;</hi> from the Truth of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> to the <hi>Dreams</hi> of ſome here and there— What ſhall I ſay? ſome diſaffected <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> or <hi>Man of State.</hi> To proceed: By whom was the World made? <hi>By me,</hi> ſaith the Divine Wiſdom. Whence had the <hi>Stars</hi> their <hi>Influences?</hi> the Celeſtial Orbs their Motions? <hi>Vegetables</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals</hi> their Vertues? Who was it, in fine, that made every thing out of nothing by <hi>one</hi> word; and by <hi>another</hi> drew <hi>Order</hi> out of that <hi>Confuſion?</hi> This was all done, <hi>Per me</hi> ſtill; and the original of <hi>Government</hi> was as much the work of Gods <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100684:6"/>as the <hi>Creation</hi> was of his <hi>Power.</hi> The holy Fathers ſpeak ſo home, and ſo unanimouſly to this point, that the multiplying of Inſtances and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, would but weary out your patience, and burn day-light.</p>
               <p>You will do well to obſerve and ſtill keep in your mind, that the Doctrine of the Inſtitution of <hi>Power,</hi> as I have here delivered it, is no other than that which hath been faithfully tranſmitted unto us by the bleſſed <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> himſelf. <hi>Per me, By me,</hi> is a <hi>ſufficient Testimonial</hi> that it is of <hi>Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> But then there is <hi>Reges</hi> and <hi>Regnant,</hi> yet to come. And here we are to take notice of the <hi>extent</hi> and <hi>term,</hi> or <hi>duration</hi> of this <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> It is ſpoken to all Kings, to all <hi>Soveraign Powers,</hi> under what form ſoever; and ſo it is to all <hi>People,</hi> in all <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> at all <hi>Times,</hi> and for ever; without any ſort of <hi>condition, limitation,</hi> or <hi>restriction,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Cuſtoms, Decrees,</hi> or any <hi>Political Sanctions,</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions:</hi> I ſpeak this with all reverence imaginable to the Dignity of <hi>Humane Laws,</hi> and to the Order of <hi>Humane Society.</hi> But my meaning is, that as <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Fountain,</hi> the inexhauſtible <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Power;</hi> and incomprehenſible in all his Attributes, beyond what the Spirit of a Man is able to conceive: ſo we cannot without <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> ſo much as fancy to our ſelves, that <hi>Wiſdom it ſelf</hi> can ever miſtake its meaſures: Which Contemplation brings me to the point I am now ſpeaking of; which is, That all <hi>Humane Powers</hi> are but as Emanations out of the Boſome of Gods Eternal Providence, without any other reſpect to mankind, than as a Rule and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100684:7"/>for them to Govern by: Not but that Men are apt, inſtead of carrying the <hi>Copy</hi> to the <hi>Original,</hi> to bring down the <hi>Original</hi> to the <hi>Copy.</hi> But ſtill <hi>By me Kings reign,</hi> is a <hi>Doctrine</hi> not to be <hi>questioned;</hi> an <hi>Authority</hi> not to be <hi>diſputed,</hi> and a <hi>Foundation</hi> never to be <hi>undermined.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it will be ſaid perchance, That the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality</hi> of this Propoſition goes too far, and that the Canon of our <hi>Scripture</hi> is no Rule to a <hi>Pagan:</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, This is a Truth founded in reaſonable <hi>Nature;</hi> A <hi>Truth</hi> that every Man finds writ in his <hi>Heart;</hi> and in ſhort, a <hi>Truth</hi> that is calculated for all <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians,</hi> for all Religions, for all Nations, <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Barbarous,</hi> with a particular regard to the <hi>Comfort,</hi> the <hi>Peace,</hi> and the <hi>Well-being</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi> There are in the World that take upon them to bound <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Powers,</hi> by certain <hi>State-Meaſures</hi> and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, according to popular Conceptions of their own, and to furniſh plauſible Arguments to the common People upon this ſubject. But theſe are Governments of man making, not of Gods: and a ſort of Kings, that King <hi>Solomon</hi> never dream't of, in his <hi>Per me Reges Regnant; By me Kings Reign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have had here the Dignity of Power ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the Officer Commiſſioned; and the laſt word of my Text does now hand us forward, from the <hi>Faculty</hi> and <hi>Signature</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> to a Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it in the <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> with a reſpect to the right <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> or <hi>Abuſe</hi> of it. I ſhall not need to enlarge upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100684:7"/>it, that in all Power there is firſt a Regard to be had to the Character; and then again to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> or <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of it. The firſt is <hi>wholy Divine</hi> and <hi>Perfect;</hi> the ſecond lyable to the <hi>frailties</hi> and paſſions of <hi>Fleſh and Blood;</hi> ſo that as the <hi>Divinity</hi> of the <hi>one</hi> ſhall in no ſort excuſe the <hi>perſonal fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of the <hi>other:</hi> Neither ſhall the <hi>Sacred Image of God</hi> that is ſtamped upon <hi>Sovereignty</hi> ſuffer any diminution of <hi>Reverence</hi> for theſe miſtakes; on the other hand it is not in the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Perſon</hi> to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>-nking</hi> the <hi>Office;</hi> and much leſs in the Power of the <hi>People</hi> to call <hi>Gods immediate Miniſter</hi> to an <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count:</hi> It is <hi>Per me Reges; by me Kings:</hi> Not <hi>per me Senatus Populuſque:</hi> By me <hi>the Senate and the People Reign,</hi> in an Imperial State. There is no room for <hi>Intruders,</hi> betwixt the <hi>King of Kings</hi> and his <hi>Vice-gerents.</hi> Be this ſpoken to the ſhame of <hi>Calumniators,</hi> and to the confuſion of thoſe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Trying the <hi>Crooked</hi> by the <hi>Streight,</hi> bring the <hi>Streight</hi> to the <hi>Crooked;</hi> and force the <hi>Oracles</hi> of the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> to the bent of their own <hi>Carnal Luſts, Intereſts</hi> and <hi>Deſigns.</hi> Is a Prince <hi>Religious, Juſt, Gracious, Merciful?</hi> Is he <hi>Reſolute</hi> in <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Temperate</hi> in <hi>Peace?</hi> Is he <hi>Firm</hi> to his <hi>Honour,</hi> to his <hi>Word,</hi> to his <hi>Conſcience?</hi> Is he <hi>Tender</hi> of his <hi>People</hi> and his <hi>Friends,</hi> and <hi>placable</hi> to his <hi>Enemies?</hi> Is he <hi>all this,</hi> and as much more as might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to make up the moſt <hi>Conſummated Character</hi> of a <hi>Governour after Gods own Heart? Per me Regnat, He Reigns by me.</hi> On the contrary, is his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Heavy</hi> upon us by <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> by <hi>Injustice,</hi> by all ſorts of <hi>Vexations? Per me Regnat</hi> ſtill. The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100684:8"/>
                  <hi>Good</hi> and the <hi>Bad</hi> Prince are <hi>Creatures</hi> both of the ſame <hi>Power,</hi> ſtamped with the ſame <hi>Impreſs,</hi> and as inviolably <hi>Sacred</hi> the <hi>one</hi> as the <hi>other.</hi> Happy is that People however whoſe bleſſed Lot it is to fall under the influence of ſo <hi>Divine</hi> a <hi>Conjunction;</hi> as when the <hi>Perſon</hi> that <hi>Governs</hi> is <hi>previouſly adapted</hi> by <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> to all the <hi>ends</hi> of his <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Imployments.</hi> I cannot paſs this Hint without a thankful Conſideration of Gods infinite Mercy and Goodneſs to us, in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Our Dear</hi> and <hi>Dread Sovereign.</hi> It is no flattery, but <hi>Duty, Truth</hi> and <hi>Gratitude,</hi> to own the Comforts we enjoy in the <hi>Confluence</hi> of all thoſe Royal Endowments in the <hi>Ruler</hi> whom God hath ſet over us, which may make a <hi>Prince, Great</hi> and <hi>Glorious,</hi> and a <hi>People Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</hi> A Bleſſing that hath ſcarce left us any Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Comforts further to pray for, beyond the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of what by Gods Mercy we at this day enjoy. A Prince under whoſe Protection we are ſafe; in whoſe Clemency we are free and eaſie: A Prince whoſe <hi>Benignity</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> hath left us no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to <hi>fear;</hi> and whoſe overflowing <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> hath hardly left us any Place for <hi>more</hi> to <hi>hope</hi> for. It would be as endleſs to Enumerate the Mercys that we are <hi>poſſeſt</hi> of, as it would be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to ſay what we <hi>want.</hi> Bleſſed be Gods Holy Name, for the ſhare we have, (all that are here preſent) in ſo ineſtimable a Bleſſing; a Bleſſing that hath been ſnatched out of the very Jaws of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeveral deaths, by as many Miracles. May the ſame <hi>Watchful, Powerful Providence,</hi> ſtill and for ever cover that ſacred Head: and preſerve Him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100684:8"/>hereafter as hitherto, from his open, and from his ſecret Enemies; and in one word, from the raging of the Seas and from the tumults of the People. I have done with the Diviſion of my Text in the ſeveral parts of it upon the heads of <hi>Government:</hi> It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains only to ſpeak a word of the <hi>whole,</hi> by way of <hi>Innuendo</hi> or Application, taking it all together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Per me Reges Regnant, By me Kings Reign.</hi> Theſe few words in the Context, Preach this Doctrine to all <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Governours: By me, it is you Monarchs of the Earth,</hi> ſaith the Almighty, <hi>that you Reign: You hold your Commiſſion at my Will and Pleaſure;</hi> There is no <hi>other Power</hi> that hath any thing to do with you. I have placed you in the <hi>Throne</hi> of my <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> inveſted you with the <hi>Robes</hi> of <hi>Dignity.</hi> I have armed you with the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited all the <hi>Enſigns</hi> of <hi>Majeſty</hi> in your hands: Not for <hi>your ſelves</hi> to <hi>Alienate</hi> or <hi>Diſpoſe</hi> of, but in Truſt, as you ſhall Anſwer it at my Tribunal. Who then ſhall dare to <hi>Oppoſe You?</hi> You <hi>Reign</hi> by <hi>my Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and who ſhall preſume to diſpute your <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</hi> You Reign in my <hi>Name,</hi> and who ſhall Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion your <hi>Deputation?</hi> In few words, You Reign <hi>for</hi> me, <hi>in</hi> me, <hi>by</hi> me; ſtick to the Order I have given you, and execute it. I will-have no <hi>ſharers</hi> in Royalty; I will ſuffer no <hi>Popular</hi> Competitions, whether the <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Subject</hi> ſhall be <hi>uppermost;</hi> or, which is the ſame thing, whether <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man</hi> ſhall be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</hi> Do you maintain the <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of your <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> and I'le maintain the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credneſs</hi> of your <hi>Perſons.</hi> Do not ſuffer your
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100684:9"/>ſelves to be tranſported in the Contemplation of the <hi>dazling Splendor</hi> of a <hi>Crown:</hi> But look up to the <hi>Original</hi> of all your <hi>Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> in whom you <hi>Live,</hi> you <hi>Move</hi> and have your <hi>Being:</hi> and by whom <hi>Kings Reign, Per me Reges Regnant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is time now that I ſpeak a word to the <hi>Subject,</hi> upon the point of the <hi>Obligation</hi> of his <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> for the <hi>ſame Power</hi> (as I have ſaid) which <hi>ordains Kings</hi> to <hi>Command, obligeth Subjects</hi> to <hi>Obey.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100684:9"/>
               <head>The Second Part.</head>
               <p>IN this member of the Partition I ſhall obſerve the ſame Method of Diſtribution I did in the former. <hi>Per me, &amp;c. By me Kings Reign.</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>God</hi> makes <hi>Kings,</hi> and Commiſſions them to <hi>Govern.</hi> Do they Govern well? Thank <hi>God</hi> and bleſs <hi>Heaven</hi> for it. Do they <hi>Miſgovern?</hi> There is no affronting the <hi>Miniſter</hi> upon any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whatſoever, without falling foul upon the <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and conſequently breaking in upon the <hi>Divine Authority it ſelf.</hi> The common Objection upon this Topique is this; <hi>Rulers are to be a terror to Evil Doers, not to thoſe who do well;</hi> and that the Almighty Wiſdom never gave a Commiſſion of <hi>Power</hi> to deſtroy the main Ends of <hi>Government,</hi> which conſiſts in the <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</hi> Put caſe that this Power may be ſometime perverted. Is Fire and Water ever the leſs neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the Uſe and Comfort of <hi>Life,</hi> becauſe of now and then a <hi>Deluge</hi> or <hi>Conflagration?</hi> The <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility</hi> of an abuſe of Power is <hi>Inconteſtable;</hi> for a Prince cannot Defend or Protect his People, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch a force as may enable him to oppreſs them. But what need many words? Every man ſtands or falls to his own Maſter: he that <hi>gives,</hi> may <hi>take;</hi> he that <hi>ſets up,</hi> may <hi>caſt down. By me Kings Reign,</hi> is excluſive of <hi>any other Commiſſion.</hi> It ſounds as much, <hi>as by me alone they Reign:</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100684:10"/>Which is all one with ſaying in the Inference, <hi>To me alone ſhall they account for the Execution of their Truſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be well, if all the Deſpiſers of Dignities, and the Murmurers againſt the ordinary Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Gods Providence in the Government of the World, would thoroughly weigh and conſider the Force, the Intent and Authority of this ſame <hi>Per me,</hi> in my Text, before they enter into Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Expoſtulations with God himſelf, about the Prerogative of his Ordinance of <hi>Power;</hi> or with Gods Miniſters, about certain <hi>imaginary Conditions,</hi> which they fancy to be imply'd or included in their Original Grant. If they would but give themſelves time for one ſober Thought upon this matter, it is impoſſible but they muſt be convinced of the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Folly of all thoſe <hi>Popular Schemes</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemes</hi> of Power, which <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Carnal Policy</hi> have faſhioned to themſelves. Are they afraid of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and not of <hi>Anarchy?</hi> The <hi>one,</hi> at the worſt, is only <hi>Perſonal, Temporary, Local;</hi> the <hi>other</hi> extends to <hi>all Men,</hi> to <hi>all Times,</hi> to <hi>all Purpoſes,</hi> to <hi>all Places,</hi> and Embroyls <hi>Humane Society</hi> in a <hi>Civil War</hi> over the Face of the whole Earth. But what is it at laſt that the Troublers of <hi>Publique Order</hi> contend for? Would they be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ppermost?</hi> There is no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ppermoſt</hi> upon a <hi>Level;</hi> and that's the very point before us. As for <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> there's no ſuch thing, where all is <hi>Common.</hi> Our Reaſon tells us ſo, and upon woful <hi>Experience</hi> we have found it ſo. There is no thought of removing the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100684:10"/>bounds that God hath ſet us: no place for <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Refining</hi> upon the Regulations of <hi>Providence; Government</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> are <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:</hi> God hath joyned them, and Man is not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them. It hath a more pardonable appearance, I muſt confeſs, to wage War with <hi>Man,</hi> then with <hi>God.</hi> But what is the difference betwixt ſaying to the Almighty, We will have none of <hi>your Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours;</hi> and we will have none of your <hi>Government. Non te abjecerunt, Sed me,</hi> ſays God to <hi>Samuel, They have not caſt you off, but in you, Me</hi> they have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. For it is not only <hi>Per me, By me,</hi> But <hi>Pro me, For me,</hi> that <hi>Kings Govern:</hi> That is to ſay, It is in <hi>Gods ſtead,</hi> as well as by his <hi>Divine Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> that they <hi>Reign;</hi> they are covered over with the <hi>Rayes</hi> of his <hi>Glory,</hi> and are the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> as well as the <hi>Creatures</hi> of his <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Per me (By me)</hi> that Kings Reign, is a word of <hi>Comfort</hi> to the <hi>Obedient,</hi> ſeeing they have the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> of Heaven and Earth for their <hi>Protector:</hi> and it is a word of <hi>Terror</hi> on the other hand, to the Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born or Rebellious; when they conſider that they Fight againſt <hi>God,</hi> and have the Lord of Hoſts for their <hi>Avenger.</hi> And there is no place neither for doubting whether it be <hi>Per me,</hi> or not; for <hi>Truth it ſelf</hi> hath made <hi>Proclamatation</hi> of it, in the very Syllables of my Text. There ſeems to be a certain kind of <hi>Rhetoritical Dignity</hi> in the very <hi>Marſhaling</hi> of the <hi>words;</hi> a particular <hi>Emphaſis</hi> in this ſame <hi>Per me,</hi> that puts a little ſtop to a mans thought, as if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100684:11"/>it were to beſpeak a Reverence for that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows: the very <hi>stile</hi> imports a Declaration, with a <hi>Be it known to Men and Angels,</hi> to <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> that <hi>by me Kings Reign.</hi> So that as the <hi>Obedient</hi> are ſure of <hi>Gods Favour</hi> and <hi>Indulgence,</hi> ſo the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty takes to <hi>Himſelf</hi> all the <hi>Indignities</hi> that are offered to <hi>Majesty.</hi> They that make no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of laying Violent hands upon the <hi>Thrones</hi> or the <hi>Perſons of Kings,</hi> would not ſpare the Sovereign Lord of Heaven and Earth, if they could <hi>reach</hi> him. Whoſoever ſtrikes at the Divine <hi>Order</hi> of the World, ſtrikes at the Power and Wiſdom that Created it. Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that <hi>Order,</hi> and what's the remaining Maſs without it, more than the <hi>Chymiſts Caput Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> that ſerves for nouſe or purpoſe?</p>
               <p>I cannot but take notice here, over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, of the Indubitable <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Aſſertion;</hi> that <hi>By me Kings Reign;</hi> carries a much greater weight and force with it, then (Kings Reign by <hi>Me</hi>) the latter imports only a bare Anſwer to a plain Queſtion. As if a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould ſay, <hi>By whom do Kings Reign? By me,</hi> ſays my Text. The other with a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Energy, determines the Queſtion by <hi>Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</hi> He goes too far that doubts. The whole <hi>Scheme</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> is accurately Delineated and in the uttermoſt extent of it, as fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in theſe four words: The very <hi>Stamp</hi> conſecrates the <hi>Matter;</hi> and challenges a <hi>Reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> even before and without knowing what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100684:11"/>our Obedience is to be exerciſed upon. For all the meaſures we have of Good or Evil, are the proportion our Thoughts, Words and Actions hold to the Holy Will and Pleaſure of Our Heavenly Father. It is <hi>Per me,</hi> that teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>People</hi> their Duty, ſets them Right, and keeps them right: It prevents Miſtakes, clears all Cavils, and anſwers all Pious Ends: And in all caſes of Difficulty, Claim or Diſpute, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould we fly, but to the <hi>Original</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> with our laſt <hi>Appeals?</hi> It is <hi>Per me</hi> in fine, and only <hi>Per me,</hi> that decides all Controverſy.</p>
               <p>We are now come in courſe to the two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining parts of my Text, <hi>Reges</hi> and <hi>Regnant, Kings</hi> and <hi>Reign.</hi> Theſe words give the People to underſtand, that their Governors are Gods Miniſters, and ſo there is no medling with them; and as the <hi>Prerogatives</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> are <hi>Gods Powers,</hi> ſo there is no controulling them.</p>
               <p>It would be hard after all this, yet if the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of <hi>Royalty</hi> and <hi>Royal Preheminences,</hi> ſhould not find ſomthing at laſt to ſay for themſelves in <hi>Excuſe,</hi> at leaſt, if not in <hi>Defence</hi> of their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from the Doctrine of the Revealed Will of God, as we read it both in his <hi>Holy Word,</hi> and in the common Principles of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi> It is their way to hold their Diſciples in hand, that the <hi>Per me</hi> here in the Text, doth not ſo much import an <hi>Authoritative Inſtitution,</hi> as a <hi>Permiſſion</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> as if <hi>Order</hi> were the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100684:12"/>work of <hi>Paſſion, Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Chance:</hi> and an effect rather of <hi>Humane Neceſſity,</hi> then of <hi>Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</hi> The very <hi>fancy</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Permiſſion,</hi> is little leſs then <hi>Blaſphemy:</hi> for it lays the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all <hi>Policy,</hi> in <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Confuſion;</hi> ſo that out of <hi>War,</hi> and from plain <hi>Cutting of Throats,</hi> comes forth the <hi>Whimſey</hi> of their diſtinction of a <hi>Divine Permiſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are others again, that will allow <hi>Kings</hi> to <hi>Govern</hi> as <hi>Gods Miniſters;</hi> but for the behoof of the <hi>People;</hi> infer a forfeiture of their <hi>Right</hi> to <hi>Govern,</hi> from a violation of their <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> Theſe People are not aware, that the <hi>Character</hi> does not depend upon the <hi>Administration:</hi> for whatever the <hi>Man</hi> be, the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Gods Ruler</hi> ſtill, and the <hi>People</hi> are ſtill the <hi>Kings Subjects.</hi> The <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> I ſay, does not diſſolve the <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> To ſumm up all in a few words; <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>Gods Deputies,</hi> and the <hi>Powers</hi> of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> are of no leſs <hi>Authority</hi> than the <hi>Character</hi> of their <hi>Creation.</hi> It is God that is the Author of both; and the <hi>Duty</hi> of our <hi>Allegiance</hi> is of the ſame extraction with the <hi>function</hi> of the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> What is <hi>Reigning,</hi> without <hi>Subjection?</hi> What's the <hi>Dignity</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> without the <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of <hi>Submiſſion</hi> or <hi>Obedience?</hi> Or what is <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> it ſelf, but ſuch a Chain of <hi>Connection,</hi> as if but one Link of it be taken out, the whole Frame would be in danger to fall to pieces? To paſs now from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> to the <hi>Application.</hi> How vain, how fooliſh, and how impious is it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100684:12"/>for <hi>men</hi> to <hi>contend</hi> with an invincible, and <hi>irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible Power,</hi> and to oppoſe <hi>falſe Gloſſes</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings,</hi> to the undeniable voice of Truth? In a word, the Foundations of Power are laid in the Decrees of God, and there is no undermining of them. <hi>By me Kings Reign;</hi> denounces a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand woes to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndutiful</hi> and <hi>Seditious.</hi> Who ſhall dare to ſay they <hi>ſhall not</hi> Reign, when God ſays <hi>they ſhall?</hi> And eſpecially upon the Terms of a <hi>Qui reſistunt ſibi ipſi condemnationem ferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This minds me of the Celebrity of this day; a day for <hi>Sackcloath</hi> and <hi>Aſhes:</hi> A day of <hi>Blackneſs</hi> and <hi>Horror:</hi> A day not to be <hi>mentioned,</hi> not to be <hi>thought</hi> of, but with <hi>weeping Eyes,</hi> and <hi>bleeding Hearts:</hi> A day of <hi>Sin,</hi> and a day of <hi>Judgment,</hi> meeting in the <hi>ſame Act;</hi> as in a kind of deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Contention, which of the two ſhould exceed the other. No Age, no Story can match either the <hi>Tranſcendent Degree,</hi> or the <hi>Daring Pomp</hi> and <hi>Ostentation</hi> of this wickedneſs. In ſhort, behold a Great, a Glorious, and a Gracious Prince, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon a Stage as a <hi>Criminal</hi> of State: <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, Tried</hi> and <hi>Sentenced</hi> as a <hi>Traytor</hi> to his own Subjects; and his Head ſevered from his <hi>Body</hi> by the <hi>Common Ax,</hi> under a form of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> You have here before you the fruit of a <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,</hi> that perfected the Ruine of <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> in the <hi>Murder</hi> of their <hi>Sovereign.</hi> The Common People felt on't too; and by contending for an <hi>unnatural Freedom,</hi> became the moſt wretched and contemptible of <hi>Slaves:</hi> I ſhall not need to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100684:13"/>run into Hiſtory, and rifle the <hi>Journals</hi> of thoſe days, for inſtances of Mercileſs, and of Inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cruelties. The Havock that was made upon the <hi>Subjects Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties;</hi> the <hi>Depreda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> upon the Revenues of the <hi>Crowns;</hi> the <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> of <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Orphans,</hi> the <hi>Sacrilegious</hi> abuſe of <hi>Holy Places,</hi> and <hi>Holy things,</hi> the concurring eviednces of the <hi>numerous Train</hi> of crying ſins which were caſt in, to enflame the Reckoning. This was our miſerable condition. <hi>This,</hi> and as much <hi>worſe,</hi> as it is poſſible for any man to imagine. And how could it well be otherwiſe, ſo long as the Laws were either ſilenced, or turned like Guns againſt their Maſter: and all Controverſies left to the Deciſion of the Sword?</p>
               <p>What have I to do now, beloved Chriſtians, but to beſeech you to ponder well theſe things, and by a cloſe and affectionate application of matters, to ſee what good may be drawn out of evil. Here was <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> with a <hi>Vengeance.</hi> A <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with all <hi>ſorts of Sins,</hi> to draw on <hi>all ſorts</hi> of <hi>Calamities:</hi> and the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> ſtill treading upon heel of the <hi>wickedneſs.</hi> I would beg of you, as you love God and your Sovereign, your Souls, Bodies, Liberties and Eſtates; as you tender your Religion, your Country, Peace of Conſcience, and a Good Name; do but look back now into the leading cauſes to theſe diſmal effects. Conſider the Reaſonable <hi>Tendency</hi> and <hi>Operation</hi> of them; and how naturally one thing paſſes into another through the whole ſeries of this Hiſtory, from firſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100684:13"/>to laſt. You will find upon the ſcrutiny, that this Bloody <hi>Rebellion</hi> began in <hi>Thought, Thoughts</hi> broke into <hi>hard Words,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Words</hi> were followed with <hi>Blowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They began firſt with <hi>Jelouſies, Fears, Miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, Miſinformations, Invidious Reflections, Falſe Reports, Falſe Appearances</hi> of things; and from thence, ſprung impotent <hi>Paſſions, Provoking Language, Bold</hi> and <hi>Intemperate Words,</hi> Audacious <hi>Prints</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> in diminution of the <hi>Royal Dignity, Character</hi> and <hi>Adminiſtration:</hi> for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the <hi>Prince Cheap</hi> and <hi>Contemptible,</hi> And at the ſame time, <hi>Clamorous Remonstrances</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> were blown about to render him as <hi>Odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> to the Common People; while the multitude in the mean while were miſled by <hi>falſe Doctrines</hi> about the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Sacredneſs</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> by <hi>falſe Notions</hi> of <hi>qualifying Conditions,</hi> caſes of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment miſ-ſtated, falſe Deſcants</hi> upon the <hi>Lawes;</hi> and the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> ſet above the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the <hi>Prince:</hi> Theſe were the intoxicating Amuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that poyſoned the Underſtandings of the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; this was that Licence that put things to extremities; and without conſideration either of Heaven or Hell, hurried us into thoſe barbarous confuſions that brought <hi>Charles the Firſt of happy memory</hi> to the <hi>Scaffold.</hi> This was the Root of all our Woes; and from hence we may gather the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſetting a Guard upon our <hi>Actions,</hi> our <hi>Lips</hi> and our very <hi>Thoughts.</hi> Upon our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> not only by the excluſion of <hi>raſh Cenſures,</hi> but with a regard to the <hi>reverence</hi> of <hi>Imperial Edicts</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100684:14"/>
                  <hi>Commands.</hi> And ſo upon our <hi>words;</hi> for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> is a foul ſtep towards the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heading</hi> of him. The wounding of him in his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> is only a ſlyer way of ſtriking him to the <hi>Heart.</hi> But pray take notice, I do not ſpeak of <hi>Words</hi> only of <hi>Outrage</hi> and <hi>Diſreſpect;</hi> for the <hi>ſins</hi> of <hi>Omiſſion</hi> are ſins of <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> in <hi>this</hi> caſe: the want of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> is a grand failure in <hi>Duty.</hi> Neuters are loſt to the ends and ſervice of <hi>Government;</hi> and <hi>men grow cold by example.</hi> The ways of <hi>Flattery</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> are in ſome ſort ſomewhat akin. That's the moſt dangerous <hi>flattery</hi> that is covered under an artificial appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Reproof;</hi> and that the moſt Popular and <hi>Operative Calumny,</hi> that is couched under the countenance of <hi>Good Faith, Compaſſion</hi> and <hi>Reſpect;</hi> with the ſting of a <hi>But</hi> in the tail of it. We are not only to <hi>Obey Kings,</hi> but to <hi>Pleaſe</hi> them alſo, in all things not repugnant to the will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of a juſt and a gracious God. Nay we do but diſcharge our ſouls towards God himſelf in ſo doing. Let me add, that <hi>Obedience</hi> at laſt is not ſo much the <hi>Ornament</hi> of a Chriſtian, as a perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory <hi>Obligation</hi> upon him: a <hi>Duty</hi> that he is bound to, upon a <hi>Penalty.</hi> But to <hi>perfect</hi> the <hi>Character,</hi> there muſt be certain <hi>free-will offerings</hi> over and above: There muſt be a <hi>study</hi> to <hi>pleaſe,</hi> and <hi>indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry</hi> to find out what <hi>will</hi> pleaſe; a Joy in the <hi>Diſcovery</hi> of it, and <hi>Cheerfulneſs</hi> in the <hi>Performance. Lord,</hi> cries out a <hi>Pagan</hi> upon this Topique, <hi>If I had known thy Will, my Obedience ſhould have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented thy Command:</hi> Shall the <hi>Feet</hi> preſume to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100684:14"/>direct the <hi>Head?</hi> or the <hi>Animal Nature</hi> take upon it ſelf to give Laws to the <hi>Reaſonable?</hi> Such as the <hi>Soul</hi> is to the <hi>Body,</hi> ſuch is the <hi>Ruler</hi> to thoſe that God's Wiſdom hath placed in a ſtate of <hi>Subjection.</hi> 'Tis the <hi>Office</hi> of the <hi>One</hi> to <hi>Direct,</hi> and of the <hi>Other</hi> to <hi>Excuſe;</hi> without the <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputable Authority</hi> of the <hi>One,</hi> the <hi>Obedience</hi> of the <hi>Other,</hi> is but Precarious; and it is left at the choice of the <hi>Multitude,</hi> whether they ſhall think fit to be <hi>Above,</hi> or <hi>Below;</hi> what <hi>Government</hi> to Reſolve upon, or whether there ſhall be any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment or no. My words are too ſcant for my affections, and my <hi>Time</hi> for my <hi>Matter:</hi> But before I Conclude, I beſeech you turn your Eyes yet once back again upon the <hi>Judicial Tragedy</hi> that hath occaſioned this <hi>Anniverſary.</hi> Be not impoſed upon hereafter by <hi>falſe Maxims</hi> and <hi>Rumors;</hi> let us be Wiſe, though at the coſt, upon Miſerable Experiment, of <hi>Royal Blood,</hi> and <hi>Three deſolated Kingdoms. Beware of Wolves in Sheeps clothing.</hi> May God open your Eyes, that you may ſee and diſcern the Bleſſings which you do this day enjoy; and grant that the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the laſt Age may be documental to the preſent, and thoſe Ages that are yet to come. In a word, I ſhall commend to every one this General Rule to walk by. Where ever you find <hi>private Medlers</hi> in <hi>Politicks,</hi> commenting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kings <hi>Prerogatives;</hi> or <hi>haranguing</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> upon the ſubject of <hi>Male-Adminiſtration;</hi> know it to be a <hi>ſeditious Poſt,</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> that they have taken up, for the <hi>undermining</hi> of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100684:15"/>
                  <hi>Grown:</hi> and that there is moſt certainly a Snake under that <hi>Leaf.</hi> Theſe are not <hi>Liberties</hi> to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>given</hi> or <hi>taken;</hi> for when men are once poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with croſs Principles, ſo as to ſet up <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> againſt <hi>Duty,</hi> to make <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King, Plaintiff</hi> and <hi>Defendant;</hi> the <hi>Honeſter</hi> the men are, the more <hi>deſperate</hi> is the <hi>Conſpiracy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not unmindful that I have paſſed my, meaſures; but it is the goodneſs of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence many times to turn <hi>Mourning</hi> into <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing;</hi> and to improve our deepeſt <hi>Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> into an occaſion of <hi>Thanſgiving.</hi> We have proceeded thus far in a dutiful, and a ſorrowful reflection upon the moſt execrable Murder of one of the beſt of Princes; whoſe Memory ought to be for ever tender and dear to us, not only for the ſake of his <hi>Royal Blood, Function</hi> and <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> but as he was moreover the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> in tranſmitting unto us the Bleſſings, (in Compenſation of ſo ineſtimable a Loſs) which through God's Mercy we at this day enjoy, in the <hi>Life, Vertues</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of our <hi>most Gracious Sovereign, whom God long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi> A Prince, in ſhort, of <hi>Piety, Tenderneſs,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to the Perfect <hi>wiſh</hi> of all <hi>Good Men,</hi> and to the uttermoſt <hi>poſſibility</hi> of <hi>fleſh and blood.</hi> May the Spirit of Grace and Wiſdom reſt upon his Sacred Head. May his Life be long, and his Reign happy; happy in Himſelf, in His <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſort,</hi> and in a <hi>never-failing Succeſſion,</hi> to inherit the <hi>Vertues</hi> as well as the <hi>Crown</hi> of their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100684:15"/>Royal <hi>Progenitors.</hi> And it is, finally, our fault, beloved Chriſtians, if we do not contribute all that's poſſible, by a <hi>cheerful</hi> and an <hi>Indiſpenſable Reſignation</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> to the further comfort and ſatisfaction of a Prince, whom God, in a manner, miraculouſly hath placed over us. For a concluſion, I wiſh the words of my Text, <hi>Per me Reges Regnant, By me Kings Reign,</hi> which have been ſo often in my mouth, were deeply writ in your hearts; that ſo having diſcharged our Duty in this Life towards God, and our King, we may come all in the next to Reign for ever, with the King of Kings; which God of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit goodneſs grant us. <hi>In Nomine Patris, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
